第六集：昆虫类
世界上的昆虫种类繁多，数量加起比全部动物种类还要多。
There are more kinds of insects in the world than all other kinds of animals put together.
但因为它们都很渺小，
But because they are so small,
所以我们几乎看不到它们的存在有什么不平凡。
we rarely see how extraordinary they are.
有时，它们以惊人的数量在一起。
Occasionally, they assemble in astonishing numbers.
数不尽的帝王蝴蝶在墨西哥的森林里过冬。
A billion monarch butterflies hibernate in the forests of Mexico.
大量的蜉蝣在同一时间出现接着交配。
Vast clouds of mayflies emerge all at once to mate.
昆虫们正面临着无止境的挑战。
Insects face endless challenges.
它们能以自己的想法改变着自己的身体。
They can transform their bodies to meet every purpose -
眼睛长在茎上。身体变成化学武器。
eyes grow onstalks. Bodies become chemical guns.
欲了解它们如何以及为什么做出这样的事，
To discover how and why they do suchthings,
你就要进入它们的世界。
you have to enter theirworld.
在巴塔哥尼亚和智利是大量特别的甲虫的家。
Patagonia, Chile, home to one of the most extraordinary of beetles.
世界上有许多类型的甲虫，
There are many kinds of beetles in the world,
然而这只甲虫拥有昆虫界里最大的角。
but this one hassome of the biggest jaws of all.
他叫“达尔文”甲虫。
He is Darwin's beetle.
它在去往森林的途中寻找着伴侣。
He is on his way to the forest to look for a mate.
为了寻找伴侣它将运用上它的力量
Whether he gets one or not will depend on his strength...
和它的大角。
and on the size of his jaws.
它开始了它的征途。
He starts his search.
雌性甲虫可能在树干上。
A female is likely to be on a tree trunk.
以它的体形而言这棵树非常的巨大。
But trees, in this part of the world are very tall.
它的寻找将是十分漫长。
His search could be a long one.
不幸的是，雌性离它还有25米之距
Unfortunately for him, she is 25 metres above him
在树的最高处。
near the top.
雌性有着相对正常大小的角。
She has more normal-sized jaws.
雌性只需用它来摄取食物。
But thenshe only needs them for feeding.
然而雄性用它那双大角来搏斗。
But he needs immense jaws forfighting...
因为它们都有着相同的“使命”（繁殖交配）。
..because there are other males aroundwith the same mission.
在这场搏斗中光靠力量是不够的。
Sheer strength isnot enough in these battles.
这技巧就是碰到竞争对手的头部
The technique is to reach over your opponent's head
用角钩住它的翼套。
and hook your jaws under his wing-covers.
那就是为什么它们的角需要这么长
That's why his jaws are so long
而且有着奇怪的形状。
and have that odd shape.
它能抓牢对方。
He's got the grip.
现在他要把它举起。
Now he as to lift.
但还需要些力气。
And that needs strength.
其中一只需要被举起抛下。
Another lift is needed.
事实就是这样。
And that's that.
它的外壳非常坚硬帮它吸收了弹力。
Beetle armour is strong so he bounces.
胜利者继续往上爬。
The winner climbs on.
途中许多雄性准备好向它挑战。
There are more males ready to fight him up here.
她（雌性）就在最后。
And here she is at last.
但她现在好像并没有做好准备（交配）的心情。
But she doesn't seem to be in the mood.
他只好用他那大角围成一个笼子强制她行动。
So now he has to use his great jaws as a restraining cage.
他终于成功了。
Success at last.
然而死性难改，他把她抛了下去。
But the hurling habit dies hard.
昆虫的外壳有着各种不同的外形和能力。
Insects' bodies have the capacity to take on an almostinfinite variety of shapes.
那也是昆虫成功生存繁殖的原因之一。
This is oneof the keys to their success.
雄蛾并不去寻找雌蛾。
This male moth doesn't go in search of females.
他膨胀那双有着特殊味道的双羽
He inflates a pair of scented plumes
从他的腹部末端伸出来。
that protrude from the end of his abdomen.
雌性就会来找他了
And they come to him!
所有的昆虫都有着基本相同的部分...
All insects have the same basic design...
六只脚和一顶大盔甲
six legs and an armour-covered body.
但是不同的部分却变得很夸张
But the different parts can become exaggerated
来满足各自的需要
tosolve particular problems.
这只甲虫那长颈鹿似的的脖子就用来搏斗。
This beetle has a giraffe's neck in order to fight.
螳螂伪装成一花朵
A praying mantis is disguised as a flower
等待着埋伏着。
and waits in ambush.
这只螳螂运用了难以察觉的枯叶外型。
Another is almost invisible amongdead leaves.
昆虫的外壳能以丰富的颜色来伪装或交代信息。
Insects' armour can carry colours that can camouflage or communicate.
但也能由外壳转变成翅膀
But the armour can also be converted into wings
使昆虫遍布世界，
and that makes insects a globalforce,
使它们能侵占地球的每一处并在那栖息
enabling them to invade almost every habitat on earth.
在法国的南部，
In Southern France,
一只昆虫开始着其生命中最重要的一天。
one insect is starting on the most important day of its life.
旁晚，一只刚长成（出壳）的豆娘（蜻蜓）。
Dawn, and a newly hatched damselfly.
她要在日落前交配并且产卵。
She needs to mate and lay her eggs before sunset.
她成虫的时间非常短，她没有第二次机会了。
Her adult life is so short, she may not get another chance.
她的成功将依靠那脆弱的翅膀。
Her success will depend on these fragile wings.
她面临许多危险。
She faces many perils.
很少昆虫能逃脱蜘蛛的网。
Few insects can escape from a spider's web.
她的翅膀比看起来有劲。
But her wings are more powerful thanthey look.
她想和强壮的雄性配对。
She wants to mate with the strongest male.
然而，能寻找到雄性的小溪却是一个战场。
However, the stream, where she might find him, is a battle-ground.
她注视着，黑色翅膀的雄性取得最佳地盘的竞争。
She watches while dark-winged males compete for the best territories,
挥动翅膀相互威胁着，
flashing their wings at each other in threat,
或者用武力将他们的竞争对手压到水面。
or trying to force their opponents into the water.
竞争结束后，雌性用她的翅膀做暗号对胜利者说明她的到来。
Fighting finished, the female uses her wings to signal her presence to the winner.
她不匆不忙。
She won't be rushed.
如果雄性不抓住雌性的尾部，对手可能会抢走雌性。
But if he doesn't grip her with his tail, a rival might steal her.
当它们配对成功，它们交配时的外型像个心型。
As they mate, their linked bodies form the shape of a heart.
但是另一个问题来了，她产卵时会遇到很多风险。
But now she has the problem of laying her fertilised eggs and that brings new hazards.
像一些运动员那样，她会先热身
Like any athlete, she must warm her muscles for optimum performance
她们利用太阳加热翅膀。
and does so by using her wings as solar-heating panels.
想找到合适的产卵地儿就必须危险的低飞。
She must fly dangerously low if she's to find the right place for her eggs.
只有最敏捷的豆娘才能逃脱
Only the quickest damselflies escape.
安全的逃离了青蛙，
Safely past the frogs,
这些雌性找到一处合适的地方产卵。
this femalehas reached a suitable planton which to lay her eggs.
如果她们刚都幸存下来就要到水下来。
But she has to place them underwater if they are to survive.
她的翅膀看上去是一个妨碍。
For the first time, her wings seem to be a hindrance.
但事实上，她的翅膀是有一次帮了她，
But in fact, they help her yet again,
翅膀上银色的一层其实是空气，这样她就能呼吸了。
by trapping a silvery layer of air which enables her to breathe.
她尾部刺入植物的茎部在里面产下了她的卵。
She cuts into a plant stem and deposits her eggs inside.
现在，她的翅膀将是面临真正的考验。
Now herwings are going to be truly tested.
如果她不能突破水面她将会溺死。
If she can't break through the water surface, she will drown.
她圆满的成功了 。
Her day has been a complete success.
豆娘在小溪里罕见的冒险。
Damselflies seldom venture beyond their home stream.
但是一些昆虫要飞很长的距离。
But some insects fly huge distances.
九月在加拿大南部的伊利湖湖畔
September on the shores of Lake Erie in Southern Canada.
一只帝王蝴蝶正采集着花蜜。
A monarch butterfly is fuelling up on nectar.
一阵北方空气的寒冷阵风
A chill gust of Northerly air.
是它该离开的时候。
It's time to leave.
即将到来的冬天会是如此寒冷会将她冻死。
The coming winter will be so cold it would kill her.
在她的生命里她从来没有飞超过几百米。
She has never flown more than a few hundred metres in her life.
但现在她飞离伊利湖，
But now she is heading out over Lake Erie,
这是一百英里的路程。
which is a hundred miles across.
这仅仅是最伟大的动物迁徙的第一站。
This is just the first leg of one of the greatest animal migrations.
她将继续南行，利用太阳作为罗盘，
She will continue South, using thesun as a compass,
穿越美国，将是两千英里的旅程。
to cross America, a journey of 2,000 miles.
她的目的地是墨西哥的一处小而且特别的树林。
Her destination is Mexico and one small and special group of trees.
没有人知道它们是如何从这片大山林里找到这处地方的。
No-one knows how she finds them, in these great mountain forests.
她加入其他帝王蝴蝶，它们都来至各北美地区。
She joins other monarch butterflies that have travelled here from all over North America.
无数的蝴蝶挤满了这片特别的树林。
Countless butterflies crowd these particular trees,
挂满了每棵枝条。
hanging from every branch.
它们来到这里是因为冬天带来了寒冷的空气，
They come here because, although winter brings a chill to the air,
在加拿大它们不会寒冷致死。
there will not be a lethal freeze as there will in Canada.
这里的条件有利于过冬。
The conditions are perfect for hibernation.
冬眠中的帝王蝴蝶十分易受到其他动物的攻击。
Hibernating butterflies are vulnerable to predators.
但是帝王蝴蝶是有剧毒的。
But monarchs are poisonous.
然而，一些小鸟学会了祛除帝王蝴蝶其有毒的部分吃下没毒部分。
However, a few birds have learned to rip out the toxic parts and eat the rest.
它们杀死成千上万的蝴蝶，还有许多是被迫赶下了树。
They kill hundreds of thousands of butterflies and dislodge many more.
那些掉下了树的蝴蝶必须回到树上，因为夜里带里另一个“杀手”。
Those that fall must get back into the trees before nightfall brings another killer.
他们颤动翅膀想要回暖翅膀。
They vibrate their wings to warm their flight muscles.
但这是与时间赛跑。
But it's a race against time.
夜里待在地上会被冻伤的。
Night brings a lethal ground frost.
四个月过去了，那些挤在树上冬眠的蝴蝶都能存活下来。
Those that do survive, sleep safely huddled together in the trees, for four months.
温暖的春天把它们从冬眠的状态唤醒过来。
The warmth of spring wakes them from their hibernation.
大多数幸存的蝴蝶都是从加拿大飞往过来的。
The majority of the butterflies that flew here from Canada have survived.
他们吸食着至去年秋天到现在的第一口饮料。
They take their first drink since their arrival last autumn.
当越来越温暖的时候，更多的蝴蝶也将苏醒过来。
With increasing warmth, more and more butterflies awake.
不久它们将分散北移
Soon they will all disperse northwards
这片森林也将返回安宁
and tranquillity will return to this forest
直到这些蝴蝶的子孙为了逃避寒冷又再次回来这里。
untilthe great grandchildren of these butterflies return to escape the freezing Northern winter.
然而，有些昆虫，有能力生活在非常不利的环境下。
Some insects, however, have made a speciality of living in the most adverse conditions.
莫诺湖被称为美国加洲的死海。
Mono Lake is known as California's dead sea.
比海水还要咸两倍的湖水对于任何生物来说都是致命的。
It's twice as salty as the ocean and lethal to almost all life.
碱苍蝇是少数能忍受这种环境的动物之一
Alkali flies are one of the few creatures able to tolerate these conditions
实际上它们几乎没有竞争对手，
and since they have virtually no competitors,
他们数以百万的聚集在这里。
they swarm in their millions.
苍蝇是所有最成功的昆虫之一
Flies are one of the most successful of all insects.
它们有85,000不同种类
There are 85,000 different kinds
每种苍蝇都能很好的适应每处环境，甚至在这里
and among them, a perfect fly for almost every habitat, even this one.
碱苍蝇具有特殊能力，使它们能够生活在这个湖
The alkali fly has special abilities that enable it to live on this lake.
它们能到水下吃藻类。
It can walk underwater to eat algae.
纤细的茸毛收集气泡防止它们被溺死。
Fine hairs trap air bubbles that prevent it from drowning.
但最关键的是苍蝇的生理机能
But most critically, the flyhas a physiology
能中和盐的致命成分
that can neutralise the lethal levels of salt.
所以碱苍蝇支配了莫诺湖并未受到挑战
So the alkali fly's dominance of Mono Lake goes unchallenged
除了一年里的几周。
except for a few weeks of the year.
100,000的威尔逊 矶鹞迁移到了南美洲。
100,000Wilson's phalarope are migrating to South America.
莫诺湖是他们唯一休息站。
Mono Lake is their only stop-over.
这些碱苍蝇，对它们来说，却是宝贵和不可抗拒的盛宴。
These alkali flies, for them, are an invaluable and irresistible feast.
苍蝇没有防备的方法，除了飞和大量的减少。
A fly has no defence, except tofly and become lost in a vast swarm.
它需要相当的技巧来吃到飞行中的苍蝇。
It needs considerable skill to pluck an individual fly from the air.
当然这里还有许多海鸥。
There are gulls are here, too.
虽然它们抓苍蝇的技巧并没有那么好。
Though their fly-catching techniques are not so refined.
在这四个星期里，矶鹞体重增加了一倍。
In four weeks, the phalaropes double their weight.
它们再度向南出发。
Then they set off again, heading south.
海鸥也在它们后出发。
Leaving the gulls behind.
苍蝇种群数量几乎没有受到影响。
The size of the fly population has scarcely been affected.
对它们来说，数量就是一种防御。
For them, sheer abundance is defence enough.
嗡嗡响
BUZZING
但对于某些昆虫，防御是一项十分复杂的事情。
But for some insects, defence is a much more complicated affair.
在南非的A甲虫。（oogpister就用A来做代称吧）
An oogpister beetle in South Africa.
它捕食蚂蚁。
He hunts ants.
吃蚂蚁，可给予它的不只是填饱肚子。
Eating ants may give him more than just nourishment.
它可能会找些其他帮助打退它的敌人。
He may get something else from them that helps him fight his enemies.
蚂蚁发动反击，并咬他的脚踝。
The ants launch a counter-attack and nip his ankles.
但他只是用踢飞的方式（哈哈）
But he simply kicks them out of the way.
勇敢的蚂蚁击退了它...
The valiantants drive him off...
直接进入真正的危险。
straight into real danger.
一只猫鼬。
A mongoose.
它是好奇的动物。
It's inquisitive.
但它也提防着A。
But it's also wary of the oogpister.
黑和白的图案是种警告信号。
A black and white pattern is a warning signal.
甲虫它瞄准着...
The beetle takes aim...
火蚁的蚁酸都被喷到了猫鼬的眼睛和嘴巴上了。
And fires formic acid straight at the mongoose's eyes and mouth.
A可能是从蚂蚁那收集了酸液。
The beetle probably collected this acid from the ants.
这无疑也是甲虫非常讨厌的酸液，但这次，它也好好利用了酸液模仿了蚂蚁的角式。
It certainly makes the beetle itself very distasteful and that, in turn, makes it worth mimicking.
这手无寸铁的小蜥蜴，背上也有着甲虫那样的警告色。
This defenceless little lizard carries the beetles' warning pattern.
也模仿着甲虫的走路样子。
It also imitates the way the beetle runs.
不是特别好，这是真的，但足够了。
Not particularly well, it's true, but well enough to
以为愚弄食肉动物它只是可能是酸烧虫。
fool predators into thinking it just might be an acid-firing beetle.
各种昆虫都有着化学武器的发展。
All kinds of insects have developed chemical weapons.
一只条纹竹节虫。
A pair of devil-rider stick insects.
它们喷射出苦味的油，□烯
They fire bitter-tasting oils, terpenes.
受到饥饿的乌鸦攻击的欧洲木蚂蚁
European wood ants under attack from a hungry crow.
蚂蚁喷射出的酸性液体使乌鸦感到刺痛
They fire the sort of acid that gives nettles their sting,
就像让人陷入棘手的麻烦。
so this is like one of us falling into a nettle patch.
但真正的化学战的大师乃是投弹甲虫。
But the master of chemical warfare is the bombardier beetle.
它可以创建剧烈的体内化学反应室
It can create a chemical reaction within it's body so violent
炽热的腐蚀性液体从它的腹部处迅速喷出。
that boiling caustic liquid explodes out of its abdomen.
通过脉冲射500次1秒
By pulsing the jet 500 times a second,
它们尾部有冷却系统以防止它被煮熟
it keeps its rear end just cool enough to prevent it being cooked.
在明尼苏达州的林地，
In the woodlands of Minnesota,
这里一种昆虫，还有另一种化学武器。
there is an insect that has another chemical weapon.
他们战斗的时候就像一名军人，勇敢的对抗全部食肉动物。
But this one fights as an army and can stand up to almost any predator.
蜂蜜辛勤的收集花蜜和转换它，储存在它们胃里，
Bees collect nectar all day and transform it, within their stomachs,
自然界营养丰富的食物，蜂蜜。
into one of nature's richest foods, honey.
数以百计的它们每日工作就是把宝贵的“负担”带回了它们的巢穴。
Hundreds of them are bringing their precious loads back to their colony in this hollow log.
它们用蜂蜜喂养着后代
The honey in their combs provides food for their young
还存储起来以应付天气的转冷或着干旱。
and for the whole colony if the weatherturns cold or there's a drought.
但是如此多的食品也吸引了小偷。
But so much food attracts thieves.
幼小的黑熊喜欢甜食。
A black bear cub has a sweet tooth.
但它从来没有遇到以前蜜蜂
But he's never come across bees before
它并不知道蜜蜂将捍卫他们的蜂蜜直到战死
and he doesn't know that they will defend their honey to the death.
蛰刺最终会导致蜜蜂自己的死亡，
Stinging is the ultimate self-sacrifice for a bee,
因为它们不能拔出倒刺。
because itcan't pull out its barbed sting.
因此，它的身体也将被撕裂。
So its body is torn apart.
蜜蜂猛烈的攻击幼熊。
The bees' attack was far too much for the cub.
但更大的挑战即将到来。
But a greater challenge is coming.
幼熊的妈妈
The cub's mother!
ANGRY BUZZING
愤怒的嗡嗡声
蜜蜂抵抗到底，熊妈妈只有一次偷一点
The bees fight so hard that she only has time to steal a single comb.
熊家庭在远离蜂巢的安全距离享用着蜂蜜
While the family enjoy their honey at a safe distance,
蜜蜂似乎被打败了
the beesappear to have been defeated.
它们的家已被毁坏
Their home has been destroyed
而它们的后代也不可避免的因为曝露在外而死去
and their young will inevitably die out in the open.
然而群体不会就这样灭亡，工人们正营救着最后真正的关键
Yet the colony is not doomed because the workers are now rescuing at least some of what really matters...
它们的蜂蜜
..their honey.
存活下来的蜜蜂们吃下和它体重相当的蜂蜜存储在它们胃里
Each survivor is able to eat its own weight in honey, storing it in its stomach.
它们会丢弃它们的后代
They will have to abandon their dying young,
但它们会保留那宝贵的蜂蜜
but they will take much of their precious honey with them
这将支撑着它们建立新的巢穴
to sustain themselves while they build a new colony.
有组织的一起工作就像昆虫里的社会化改革
Working together in such an organised society is the insects' great innovation.
那么，怎样开始
So how did it begin?
它可能已经在这样一个地方开始
It may have started in a place like this -
日本红虫的巢穴里
the nest of the Japanese red bug.
成年昆虫通常不会照顾后代，但是这种甲虫则不是
Parent insects don't usually care for their offspring but this bug is different.
幼虫以一种珍惜的树的果实为食
The young feed on fallen fruit from just one kind of rare tree.
幼虫们无法靠自己来采集，一次它们的母亲为它们收集它。
They could never find it by themselves. So theirmother collects it for them.
她先品尝每个她找到的果子
She probes every fruit she finds
以试它的成熟度
to test its ripeness
并丢弃了一个又一个
and rejects one after another.
这需要耗费几个小时
This can take hours.
最后找到一个完美的水果
At last, a perfect fruit.
一小偷
A thief!
窃取易于自己去麻烦寻找食物
It's easier to steal than find food for yourself.
两个发疯似的在挣抢，但是也正将演示一幕大变化
For both bugs, the outcome of this dispute will be life-changing.
甲虫妈妈努力的保护它的果子
As the mother struggles to keep herprize,
她的幼虫在巢穴里急躁不安
her young, back in the nest, are growing restless.
小偷得到最终胜利
The thief has won.
甲虫妈妈不知道它那饥饿的幼虫们离开了巢穴去寻找更好的养育者
The mother doesn't know that her hungry young are leaving their nest in search of a better provider.
甲虫妈妈回来了
She returns
发现它的巢穴此时已经空了
to find that her nest is empty.
她的幼虫们找食却来到了刚才那小偷的巢穴
Her young find the nest of the thief, who is herself a mother.
她回来的时候发现突然多了许多幼虫
She returns to find that she has twice as many mouths to feed.
失败者输的是当父母的立场
The loser has failed at her only chance of parenthood.
对于小偷而言，生活变得更难了
For the thief, life has suddenly got much harder.
食物无法永远吃不完
A fruitwon't now last as long as it did.
幼虫爬到它身上，要求得到更多的食物
The youngclamber over her, demanding more.
她领着果子回来了但她不得不加力度寻找食物
She returns with another fruit but her enlarged and
贪得无厌的幼虫需要更加
insatiable brood want still more.
所以她不得不没天没夜的工作找食物
So she has towork non-stop, day after day.
终于，幼虫长大到有能力自己去寻找食物
At last, the young become big enough to fend for themselves.
但她们的成功是有代价的
But their success has come at a cost.
甲虫妈妈辛勤的工作致死
The mother has worked herself to death.
现在她的身体成为了她幼虫们最后一顿食物接着离开巢穴
And now her body hasbecome their last meal before they leave home.
照顾自己的幼虫以这种方式
Looking after the young in such a way
被认为是踏入社会生活的第一步
is thought to be the first step towards living in a community.
但是，一些做出相反的合作行为的昆虫却受益
But some insects benefit from doing the opposite of collaborating.
他们互相残杀
They kill one another.
道森蜜蜂是全球蜜蜂的体形里最大的
Dawson's bee is one of the largest in the world.
它们在澳洲内陆被太阳晒干的土壤中筑巢
It nests in the baked soil of the Australian outback.
花在的沙漠这乃罕见，所以这里蜜蜂巢穴是寥寥可数
Flowers are rare in thisdesert, so colonies of these bees are few and far between.
道森蜜蜂挖掘隧道来养育的幼虫
The bees excavate tunnels fortheir young.
让人很难相信，巢穴间是如此和谐
The community is so harmonious that it's hard to believe that this place
但也是大屠杀的环境
is also the setting for mass murder.
如果一只蜜蜂糊涂的进入到别人的巢穴，主人脾气就不好了
Tempers do flare when a bee gets confused and goes down another's burrow.
不过这些都是次要的分歧
But these are minor disagreements.
巢穴的是和平的时刻，因为每一个在这里蜜蜂都是雌性
The colony is peaceful at the moment becauseevery bee here is a female.
雄性则是杀手把它们全部都杀光了
It's the males that are the killers and they are all dead.
它们的故事始于两个月前
Their story began two monthsearlier,
在雌性出现之前
before theappearance of the females.
雄性道森蜜蜂
Male Dawson's bees.
雌性才刚刚出现，逐个以挖洞的方式出现
The females are only just emerging, burrowing their way, one by one,
她们走出隧道和孵化成长
out of the tunnels where they hatched and grew up
她们的气味吸引着雄性
and their scent enflames the males.
他们体形巨大，挖掘地洞迎合搏斗
They arehuge and built for fighting.
而每一只雄性都想要占有有利的位置配对雌性
And each one wants to be in the best position to mate with a female.
一雌性出现马上引起打斗
A female emerges and immediately there's a brawl
每只雄性都想接着雌性
as every male tries to reach her.
在打斗中杀死对方这很少在动物界发生
It's very rare for animals to kill their own kind in combat,
把竞争对手刺死
but stinging and biting rivals to death
通常是唯一途径获得这些雄蜂
is usually the only way these male bees get a female.
胜利者能控制雌性，两者包在一起
A winner manages to claim a female and the pair race for cover.
同时，雌性挥之不去的气味继续吸引着失败的雄性们
Meanwhile, the female's lingering scent drives one unsuccessful male
变成了疯狂的杀戮
into a deadly frenzy.
另一个雌性，在另一斗殴事件中被捕，成为一个意外伤亡
Another female, caught in the middle of another brawl, becomes an accidental casualty.
到最后的女性出现时，全部雄蜂都死亡了
By the time the last female has emerged, every male is dead.
战役确保了强大的雄性会与最多雌性交配
The battles have ensured that the strongest males will have mated with the most females.
两个月过后变成了雌性的天下
Two months later and it's an all female world
下一代已经在地下发育着
with thenext generation already developing underground.
昆虫已经进化发展为成熟的社会而且复杂
Insects have evolved sophisticated societies that, in complexity,
实际上已经接近我们的城市生活。
are the closest thing in nature to our own cities.
在阿根廷昆虫以这种结构建立着
The insects that built this structure in Argentina
支配着周围草原的行为看上去更像是人类多于昆虫。
dominate the surrounding grasslands thanks to skills that seem almost more human than insect.
这是一个大都市，
It's a metropolis,
一个数以百万计的蚂蚁家族。
a home to millions of ants.
蚂蚁家族需要大量食物。
The colony needs a huge supply of food.
它的周围环绕着草，
It's surrounded by grass,
但蚂蚁本身无法消化叶片。
but the ants themselves can't digest a blade of it.
虽然如此，它们收集叶片。
Nonetheless, they collect it.
虽然它们是同一种类，但是它们有不同的外形和大小。
Although they're all the same species, they exist in different shapes and sizes.
个别拥有大颚的蚂蚁头脑并不发达
The heads of these big-jawed individuals are not full of brain...
但是肌肉发达。
but brawn.
它们有特别的名字
They give the species its name.
它们叫切叶蚁
They are grass cutters.
每一天他们都辛勤工作
They work all day, every day.
个头较小的蚂蚁，趴在地上，它们的工作是搬运工
The smaller ants, down on the ground, are porters with the job
搬运草片回到巢穴
of carrying the grass segments back to the colony.
它们力气很大，主要的问题就是如何取得平衡
They have great strength. Their main problem is balance.
它们扛着叶片走着运输大道赶回巢穴
Columns of them carry the grass back to the nest along highways
仿佛是罗马的笔直道路
as straight as Roman roads.
不同的成员负责不同专业的任务，跟人类一样分工明确
Different members of the colony specialise in particular tasks inmuch the same way as people do.
但是，要在人类社会，就可能会有冲突
But, as in human society, there can be problems.
对扛的蚂蚁而言有搭顺风车的同伴在会十分费力
A hitch-hiker makes one ant's job much harder.
它们不光搬运草片
And this isn't even grass.
一个蚂蚁家族一年需要半吨草
A single colony harvests half a tonneof grass a year,
比在这个平原上任何一种动物需要的还多
more thanany other animal on these plains.
但是它们本身并不吃草片，那它们收集草片作何用呢？
But since they themselves can't eat it, why do they do so?
答案在于地下
The answer lies underground.
它们拥有昆虫世界最不寻常的生存战略
They haveone of most extraordinary survivalstrategies in the insect world.
蚂蚁挖一个隧道网
The ants have dug a network oftunnels
一直向下延长可达7米多
that extend downwards for over seven metres.
在殖民地的核心是其生存的关键。真菌
At the heart of the colony lies the key to their survival. A fungus.
但是这并不是一件马虎的内务工作
But this isn't sloppy house-keeping.
这些真菌在别处都找不到
This is a fungus that is found nowhere else on earth.
这是蚂蚁们辛勤耕种
And the ants cultivate it assiduously.
大颚蚂蚁咬碎草片
The big-jawed ants chop up the grass covering it with an
唾液里含有抗生素来清洁草片
antibiotic saliva that kills every kind of fungus except this one.
蚂蚁是农民
The ants are farmers.
这些草来培育的真菌
They feed the grass to the fungus
真菌的蓬勃发展
and the fungus thrives.
蚂蚁们在巢穴的没处都培育了真菌
The ants cultivate dozens of these fungus gardens throughout the colony.
这才是他们的食物
This is what they eat.
蚂蚁家族是非常有效率的一个大家庭，可以有500万名成员
The system is so efficient that a single colony can have five million members.
真菌也是个危险
But the fungus is also dangerous.
真菌生长时排放出的二氧化碳会使整个巢穴窒息
As it grows it releases carbon dioxide that could asphyxiate the entire colony.
蚂蚁巧妙的应付这个危机
The ants' way of dealing with this danger is ingenious.
它们建造的巢穴，使之具有自动循环空气的系统。
They construct their nest so that it has an automatic air-conditioning system.
外表面是如此形状能接收微风
The outer surface is so shaped thatthe slightest breeze
通过这些中央通风口呼出混浊空气通风之用
sucks out staleair through these central vents.
同时，通风口提取外的通风口，
At the same time, fresh air is drawn down through the outer vents,
右入巢的中心
right into the heart of the nest.
我们自己的社会已经存在了几千年
Our own societies have existed for thousands of years
但昆虫社会已持续了百万年
but insectsocieties have lasted for millions.
可能有一千万不同种类的昆虫
There may be ten million different kinds of insects
200万种对应我们一个人类
and there are 200 million individuals for every one of us.
昆虫的灵活外壳和他们的适应能力
The insects' flexible armour and their adaptability
昆虫以数量最多，物种也最多样化的在我们的地球继续生活着
has made them the most abundant andthe most diverse animal group in our planet's history.
位于墨西哥的马德雷山脉
The Sierra Madre Mountains in Mexico
是世界上最美丽的一个物种的家园
are home to one of the greatest natural wonders.
十亿只帝王蝴蝶 (学名:大桦斑蝶) 给了Life摄制组一次奇妙而用充满挑战的拍摄经验
A billion bright orange butterflies offered the Life team a wonderful filming challenge.
这片帝王蝶的聚居地只有在海拔3000米的地方才能找到
The colonies are only found above 3,000 metres
摄制组在稀薄的空气中长途跋涉进行拍摄
and the team trek there slowly in the thin air.
帝王蝶迁徙的壮观场面在这里只在30年前被发现过一次
而有个人一直研究着它们
The monarch phenomenon was only discovered here around 30 years ago and one man has been studying
他是林肯．布鲁维尔教授
them every year since, Professor Lincoln Brower.
如果摄制组能够成功通让摄影机在蝴蝶群当中"飞"过
拍摄它们的迁徙
His knowledge will be essential if the team are to achieve their goal
那对于教授的研究绝对是不可多得宝贵资料
of flying a camera among the butterflies.
让人很惊讶的是帝王蝶只会来这个地区
It's amazing that the butterflies only come to this area
这个地区的面积有30乘60英里那么大
that's about 30 by 60 miles in extent.
在另一些地区有很多高树
There are other areas that have high forests,
在墨西哥的不同地区, 从这里到西方, 再到南方
in different parts of Mexico, to the west of here, to the south of here,
不过据我们所知
这里是帝王蝶唯一能够度过冬天的地方
but as far as we know, this is the only place that monarchs are able to spend the winter.
用传统的方法拍摄如此大数量的蝴蝶
The butterflies are in such numbers that filming them the traditional way,
把摄影机架在三脚架上拍摄显然是件容易的事情
from a camera on a tripod, is reasonably straightforward.
不过如果要摄影机跟随一只蝴蝶的视角
But to get a butterfly's viewpoint by flying a camera amongst
身处在蝶群中拍摄则是非常困难的
the swarms is going to be altogether more difficult.
首先, 摄制组要找到一个地方有数量庞大的蝴蝶聚集
First, the team need a spot where butterflies gather in huge numbers.
很幸运的是
林肯教授知道有一处地方每天都有成千上万的蝴蝶去饮水
Luckily, Lincoln knows a place where thousands come down to drink every day.
摄制组马上准备设备, 他们将会在那个地方呆上三天
The crew spend the next three days preparing the equipment -
一部遥控摄影机, 一堆缆索, 两个自行车轮子,
一大包石头, 还要摄制组成员的人力
a remote-controlled camera, a lot of cable, two bicycle wheels, a bag of rocks and some muscle-power.
现在他们需要做的是等待
直到蝴蝶的数量真正达到让人惊叹不已的地步
Now all they need to do is wait until the butterfly numbers reach truly impressive proportions.
在正午时分, 蝴蝶成群出动
By mid-day, the butterflies are swarming
现在是是时候让摄影机跟随蝴蝶在空中滑翔
and it's time for the camera to glide with them through the air.
倒数三声之后开始
Three and away.
太棒了, 好了, 可以停下来了
Superb. OK, let's just stop that.
绝对是让人惊叹不已
Absolutely stunning.
我们现在已经等到非常大量的蝴蝶出现, 继续拍摄吧
We've got great numbers coming in. Let's keep going
接着我们将会回头给它们一个镜头
and then we'll do a turn round shot.
这是一系列跟随着蝴蝶群拍摄的独一无二的镜头
A series of unique shots flying withthe butterflies.
不过这些都是没什么难度的了
But that was the easy part.
现在是时候把摄影机架到离地50米高树顶上面
Now it's time to get the camera 50 metres up into the tree tops.
要拍摄栖息中的蝴蝶群并非易事
因为这些蝶群的聚集并不稳定
Filming the roosting butterflies is not going to be simple, the clusters are unstable.
它们会在毫无征兆的情况下突然退散
And they can suddenly disperse without warning,
林肯教授把这种大规模的蝶群退散称作"大爆炸"!
what Lincoln calls an explosion!
这是另一次的"大爆炸", 哇, 快看看
Here'sanother explosion. Wow, look at that!
它们正在我们的头顶飞过
And they're going right over our head.
毫无疑问这实在太壮观了
不过对于摄影师Jim Spickler和Tim Fogg来说
爬上高树这的是个大问题
Spectacular, no doubt, but a real problem for the climbing team, Jim Spickler and Tim Fogg.
现在有没有一个更好的方法让我们开始拍摄?
Would it be better for us to start now?
我们会很小心翼翼地在不打扰它们的情况下拍摄
we're gonna be very careful not to disturb them,
或者说最大限度减少我们的打扰
不过貌似我们现在已经打扰它们了
or limit our disturbance, but if we do disturb them right now
它们看起来已经度过寒冬
会重新回到邻近的蝶群
it seems that they're warm enough that they could relocate to a cluster right adjacent to them,
你觉得那是真的吗?
do you think that's true?
如果你打扰了它们, 它们就会朝着某个方向飞离高树
飞到50英尺或者更加高
Well, if you disturb them they tend to fly away from the tree, 50 feet or so,
所以如果你打扰了它们, 你就会跟丢整个蝶群
so you'll lose those clusters I think if you disturb them.
你觉得它们会再度聚集到一块吗?
明天晚上? 我对此表示怀疑
Do you think they'll cluster again though, tomorrow night?Idoubt it.
我觉得它们会往下走
< I think they'll just move down.
这的确是件难事, 因为我们不知道怎么爬到这些树上去
That's really hard stuff, you know because I can't seehow we can get up the trees
不管怎样我们还是要想方设法爬到树上
and do what we have to up there,
尽可能接近任何一个蝶群而不惊动它们
close to any clusters without them flying.
我不知道如何能够把一支箭固定在树上
I just don't know how I'm gonna be able to get an arrow into the tree.
我想如果你已经选定好了一棵树
你现在就可以把箭固定在树上
I think if you picked your tree, you could put the arrow in it now.
悄悄地把缆索悬挂在半空中
The prospect of rigging cables high in the canopy, without disturbing
这些蝴蝶都是极度容易受惊
所以摄制组也许只有一次机会
the butterflies is a daunting one. They may only get one chance.
做错一个步骤就会让整个拍摄告吹
One false move and it'll all be gone.
我有一种感觉它们也许会再回来的
I had the impression that they might come back but
但是林肯教授说他们不会回来, 它们只会飞到另一棵树上
Lincoln says they just won't, they'll just move on to another tree.
所以如果我们在悬挂缆索时打扰到它们...
So we put all the rigging in, disturb them and then...
那就完了!
that's it!
挑选哪些树去悬挂缆索是个至关重要的决定
Choosing which trees to rig is a critical decision.
你看看能不能拉到"六号"树, 或是那太远了?
Can you get right to tree number six do you think, or is that too far?
他们开始用十字弓对着合适高度的树枝发射绳索
They begin by firing a line over a suitably high branch.
成功了
That'll work.
没有人, 即使是林肯教授, 也不知道那些蝴蝶将会有什么反应
Nobody, not even Lincoln, knows how the butterflies will react.
太好了, 我觉得绝对没问题
Yeah that's gonna work perfect, I think.
哦, 太棒了
OK, great.
看来我得要完全改变一下计划, 给我一点时间
I've got to do a changeover here so just give me a moment.
那里有一次"大爆炸"
There's an explosion.
但幸运的是, 那并非Jim和Tim小心悬挂缆索的那棵树
Thankfully, it's not in the trees that Jim and Tim are rigging with such care.
你能够把我往前推一点吗?
Can you just push it towards me a bit?
哎哟, 你没事吧?
Ouch.You OK?
没事, 没事, 把你的手指放开
Yep.OK, get your fingers out.
好的, 那好了
OK, that's good.
摄制组需要多用三天时间去架设悬空的缆索
接着还要花很多时间去调试
It takes another three days to get theaerial rig set up, followed by many hours of fine tuning.
请把它放平, 这才能让我们在屏幕上看不到它
Just pan it so we don't see it in the monitor, please.
最终万事俱备, 蝴蝶依然在那里
Everything is finally set and the butterflies are still there.
一, 二, 三
One, two, three.
镜头一
Take one.
太慢了
Too slow.
在开始时候就没有弄好
There was no load at the beginning
之后突然间摄影机完全停住了
and thensuddenly it just completely stopped.
镜头六
Take six.
继续. 开始时慢些, 慢些, 之后继续, 继续, 继续
Keep going. Start to slow, slow and keep going, keep going, keep going.
好的, Mike, 停住
OK, Mike, hold it.
还是不行
Not far enough.
Jim, 我们的重量不足够
We've not got enough weight, Jim.
镜头九
Take nine.
继续, Mike
Go on, Mike.
继续上, Mike. 再靠近一点, 现在开始慢一些
Go on, Mike. Get in close, Mike, now start slowing.
好的
OK.
还是未能成功, 而时间也所剩无几了
It's still not right and now time is running out.
我想是光线问题
I think the light's going.
我们还要再拍最后一次吗?
Shall we do one last take?
好的. 因为这里有一群, 我们好像错过了它们
All right. Because these ones here, we're losing the light on them.
如果顺利的话, 尝试在经过这里的时候拍一个镜头
Try and get a shot that's going past here if it's smooth.
一, 二, 三, 我们开始
One, two, three, and we're away.
镜头十七
Take 17.
一切看起来都很顺利
And it's looking good.
好的, Mike, 开始慢些, 好的, 继续, 继续这样
OK, start slowing, Mike. OK, keep it going, keep it going.
最终大功告成
Success at last.
现在这手法已证实行得通,摄制组架设更多缆索和拍了更多
With the technique now working, the crew rig more and more shots
由远而近的帝王蝶群的镜头
to give an aerial perspective on the monarch phenomenon.
林肯教授完成了给摄制组当顾问的工作后,他继续着观察研究
His work advising the crew over, Lincoln continues the observations
他做这项工作已超过25年
he's been making for over a quarter of a century.
虽然蝴蝶的数目仍然是非常巨大
Although the butterflies are still here in immense numbers,
他担心蝴蝶的生存环境正受到很大威胁
he's worried there is a threat to their survival.
蝴蝶大量涌入的数目是惊人的, 大约20亿只
The big, huge influx, maybe sometimes as many as two billion butterflies,
它们都飞到这个30乘60英里的弹丸之地
flying down into this tiny area of 30 by 60 miles,
非法的砍伐让这些蝴蝶很快就要面临绝种
is thoroughly endangered by illegal logging.
如果森林得不到保护, 如此壮观的景象就会消失
If the forest is not protected the phenomenon will be lost.
那会是灾难
It'd be a disaster.
我的意思是,这就是好比把"蒙娜丽莎"的真迹从巴黎的博物馆拿走
I mean, it would be like taking the Mona Lisa out of the Parisian museum and,
然后付之一炬
and burning it up.